Oh well, maybe we'll do something else,
right? You know, the biggest fear was
like getting trapped in a business that
you didn't want to run. And I see that
happen with so many founders. And so
very very much from the get- go, we
thought of what we wanted to build and
how we wanted to build and how we wanted
to work. So even the fact that we come
out with a new app every year, like
that's just kind of an expectation now.
And so in doing that, we can't go back
and like work on calculator V3 or
something, right? I mean, what are we
going to add? Like, we could add a ton
of new features to it, but I prefer to
say like this is the calculator that we
made and it's complete and it it does
its job really well. We're not going to
change it on you. It's not going to
suddenly like have a chatbot in the
corner.
>> Welcome to Launched. I'm Charlie Chapman
and today I'm excited to bring you the
founder designer behind Not Boring
Software, Andy Allen.
>> Andy, welcome to the show.
>> Hey, thanks for having me. We never
cross paths, but we were both in Certino
last week. And I know this one because I
follow you on Twitter and I believe you
were once again an Apple Design Award
finalist and so you were in all sorts of
things. But more importantly, I know
because you made some custom merch for
Not Boring Camera. This little extremely
cool, would you call it a keychain, I
guess, but it has all these moving
parts. It looks like a a little camera.
>> Oh, funny you should mention that.
There's one right here. Ah, there you
go. For the video video watching
audience showing it off. You can turn
the dial. And
>> I was at every single event because
Revenue Cat was sponsoring every single
event.
>> And at one of the events I was at, I was
talking to somebody and they were like,
"There's so much cool stuff here. I got
this." And he just held one up and he's
like, "It's kind of cool." And he didn't
know
your apps or anything. And he just
watched my face light up like, "Where is
he? Is he here?" And he's like, "What?"
And then I just basically vomited all
the excitement about not boring software
and all the things that you do and he's
just like, "Oh my gosh, I didn't realize
who I was talking to." So I did not
catch uh catch you or one of those. So I
don't know if you're going to bring
those to other events in the future or
if I just completely missed out. But to
be honest, I'm a little devastated.
>> Yeah, it's kind of one of the kind of
like lesser known sort of aspects of
Dubdub. Maybe my favorite, one of my
favorite aspects is just the merch game
that people bring and people make all
sorts of interesting things. So, every
year people are trying to one up each
other. People are doing like custom pins
and like special edition stickers. So,
yeah, for we came out with a camera app
this year and that's what was nominated
for the Apple Design Award. And we had
made some full-size cameras that you
might see in the background here if
you're
>> ah yes video. Yeah. in your different
themes
>> different yeah the different camera
themes and uh I thought hey let's make a
small one you know and I have young kids
and they're very into keychains at the
moment and so just made these fun little
camera keychains that you can like slide
your own little photo in the back and
has some moving parts and things like
that and yeah I just handed them I made
a bunch of them you know they're all
handmade just here uh in my house on my
Is that with a 3D printer?
>> Yeah. Yeah. But you know, you can get
like very high resolution nozzles for it
and so you can actually produce what
look like sort of manufactured parts.
Really?
>> I imagine just for the threading to work
with any degree of feeling nice, they
also need to be decently high
resolution.
>> Yeah. And it's so you can you can prod I
made like so many different colors. I
mean, I made probably like 12 or 14
different color combinations of them and
brought a whole bunch of them with me, a
big bag full and was handing them out to
apparently everyone who didn't even know
who I was or what we did. But yeah, it's
fun. I love it. You know, that's one of
my favorite parts of WWDC is just the
merch game that people bring.
>> There was uh uh the maker of Solar Watch
had sunscreen. It wasn't necessarily
customdesigned, but it was very well
tailored to the audience that's
experiencing the California sun for the
first time.
>> Yeah, I needed some of that. I came back
with a bad sunburn.
>> Let's get into Let's get into the show
here. And so before we get into not
boring apps and everything that you all
do over there, I always start the show
with the same three questions, which is
just to let people get to know who you
are. So it's where are you from? Do you
have a formal education related to what
you do? and then we'll get into like
your career leading up to starting uh
not boring software.
>> Originally I'm from born and raised in a
small town called Bethl in southwest
Alaska.
>> Yeah,
>> it's a small little fishing village.
>> How have I heard of that? Is this
wellknown or is it just because of
following you?
>> Um it's not very well known. I mean it's
>> I have like a mental picture of Bethl. I
don't know. Maybe it's like it was a
wallpaper on
>> Oh, you know, I have I have shared a
couple photos here and there. Literally,
you can see the whole town. It was like
taken in the late '8s, so sort of, you
know, I was born in the mid '80s, so I
was there at the time. You can literally
see the entire town from one photo. And
yet, you could see like individuals
walking on the street. So, it's very
like a very tiny town. There's no roads
to it. It's very isolated.
It was a very odd place to grow up in in
hindsight, but you know, when you're a
kid, it's it's just normal life.
>> That's the world living. Yeah. You're
living out there on the frozen tundra of
Alaska,
>> you know, living a very kind of
subsistence-based life. And somehow my
parents had, you know, an early Apple
Macintosh and that was kind of my
introduction to computers at the time.
And yeah, that that's where I grew up.
That was it was a very interesting
environment and I value it a lot more
now. You know, back then you you sort of
wonder why you're not, you know, living
in the big city with the rest of the
world. But you learn a certain
resourcefulness, I would say, living in
that type of environment that
unbeknownst to me was very applicable to
the startup life and the sort of indie
app life that I live now. So yeah, I
grew up there and then I did get an
education related to what I do now. It
was it was in visual communication
design from the University of Washington
in Seattle.
>> I've heard of that degree, but what is
that usually for? Cuz it's not like
digital media. It's specifically about
like communication like what Yeah. What
does that entail?
>> So the Yeah, the the more common name
might be graphic design, right? But
visual communication design is is the
kind of like you know broader context of
it. I started studying interaction
design as it was called back then. That
was like just in its infancy. This was
in the early 2000s, right? So people
were starting to design websites
and things like that and and a few like
you know ondevice interfaces were
starting to become more common. So
studied a little bit of that but mostly
it was graphic design. So my teachers
were sort of second generation like bow
house you know so they like learned from
the masters who taught at the bow house
who then came over after the war or
during the war and then taught here at
you know some great universities like
Yale and and some in the Midwest and
those taught my teachers who then
brought it over to the Pacific Northwest
and had a very kind of strict you know
international Swiss typography Raphy
sort of style of
>> everything's helvetica.
>> Everything's Yeah. One of one of three
or four or five fonts, right?
>> Everyone's worshiping at the feet of
Masimo Vignelli and and folks like that.
And it was a great foundation. You know,
it taught grid systems, a lot of things
that were very applicable to software in
hindsight.
And again, really valued that education.
But I to be honest, I wanted to be a
filmmaker. and design was meant to be
something of a side excursion to
becoming a filmmaker but found in
finding interaction design and digital
media started to learn that well you
could tell stories through interactive
media right through software and started
to pursue that more and more.
>> Okay. So that's the degree you had and
film making was kind of a passion but
you realized you could do at least
scratch that itch with maybe a little
bit well maybe not at the time but
definitely now a little bit easier of a
career path than film making or
Hollywood is. So then what did you do
out of college then? Did you get into
the field and start doing this at bigger
companies, smaller companies? Like what
did that look like? So right out out of
school, I joined an agency in Portland
called Zeba Design. And they're they
were more of an industrial design
agency, but they were starting to get
into as a lot of people at the time were
starting to get into this new field of
interaction design, right? And designing
ondevice interfaces.
So their clients were, you know, they
worked with Nike and Logitech and all
the kind of like big electronic brands
at the time. they would design the
devices and then it was kind of natural
to think well what goes on the device
what goes on the screen right the
screens were getting bigger and bigger
and taking up more of the interface
itself of the device and so we formed
this early team that was starting to
design that so I was designing a lot of
like
>> car key fob segmented you know LCD
displays and like very early touchscreen
pre iPhone and all this and doing some
like
>> installation work where you know I would
build full like working prototypes of
for like Nike and things like that for
different sports sensory training and
things like that. Got to work with some
very talented you know professional
athletes like Roger Federer to develop
like you know hand eye coordination
tests on like giant touchscreen displays
that you would play you know a
scientific version of whack-a-ole on.
So, I was like designing these games and
then testing them with professional
athletes and then fine-tuning them. All
this work was done with Nike. So, stuff
like that, you know, a real wide range
of things at this agency, but it became
very clear. I remember at one moment
designing the interface for a
multi-function printer and then seeing
that printer on the store shelf, you
know, a year or so later, right after
it'd been built, manufactured and
shipped. And it was kind of like how I
designed it but a lot was different you
know and I was like you know we went
through this whole process everybody
loved the design you know what happened
what changed right and I knew in that
moment that I needed to go where
software was actually made right there
was something I wasn't seeing there was
some constraint so is that because you
were at an agency so you had this like
total handoff you weren't part of the
next phase of dealing with trade-offs
and the realities of, you know, it
becoming a physical thing and you didn't
get to have your voice there. you could
only really extend that through your
final brief or were you even thinking
about here's the trade-offs that you
might run into like you should
prioritize this over that or did you
kind of think of your final product as
being the endstate and then it wasn't
until you saw it on the shelf that
you're like oh wait I wouldn't have made
that choice that they made here or there
yeah I mean it was more a sense that we
didn't know what language the thing was
written in you know a lot of this like a
multi-function printer or like I don't
even know what that was, right? How were
they writing that?
>> Some custom uh you know.
>> Yeah. Some very like custom, you know,
firmware and software package built on
something like a very sort of
specialized use case. Like we didn't
know what that was. We didn't know what
the limitations were. I'm doing all this
prototyping in like in Flash and
Director and things like that where you
can do some very elaborate things and
we're trying to keep it realistic, but
you know there's like all sorts of
memory constraints and animation and
refresh rates and things like that. You
have no idea what those constraints are.
You're just designing it. And so you're
handing this off. you're handing over
essentially a packet a packet of
recommendations that says this is what
we think you should do and try to do and
obviously they're hitting other
limitations that you just didn't you
couldn't account for right and I think a
lot of people are okay with that
honestly like a lot of people a lot of
designers in the field feel like well I
did my part but for me I'm a very
hands-on person you know I'm I'm the
filmmaker who wanted to like get in
there and do the edit. Right.
>> Right.
>> And apply the special effects. And
>> I very much prescribe to the kind of
David Fincher perspective of film
making, which is a director should know
how to do every role on the team, right?
Should know how to edit and do special
effects and light and do the
cinematography. Everything from like the
lowest job to the biggest job, right?
>> At a a certain level, not necessarily at
the level of the person they're hiring.
>> Exactly. Yeah. but like know it well
enough that you can create a vision
within those within those bounds. And so
I just knew that I needed to go where
software was made. And where was the
biggest software made? It was made at
Microsoft. So I never thought I would
work at Microsoft.
And this was like during the Balmer era.
So it was not a cool place for designers
to be at all.
>> Yeah.
>> It was very anti-design.
>> I don't know. lots of uh you know clear
aqua you know interfaces with Longhorn
right
>> in hindsight yeah I mean in hindsight
there was actually a lot of great work
happening uh under the hood with things
like the Zoom HD and Metro and
>> some stuff don't get me going on on my
love of uh the Zoom
>> man stuff is really aged very well I
would say um yeah so
>> but a lot of that was kind of just
bubbling under under the surface it
wasn't really known yet. And so I went
to Microsoft and worked on some early
like incubation type projects.
So worked on a twocreen like the idea
for this two-creen tablet that was
called Courier.
>> Yes.
>> The long rumored uh you know foldable
>> uh free iPad.
>> But yeah. Yeah.
>> And I mean the great thing there is you
know I met what would become my future
co-founders on my next adventure. But we
really started to develop this idea that
like technology
should be there really to service like
human creativity and most most
technology even the iPad when it came
out was very consumption focused
>> right it was Steve Jobs sitting back on
the couch book or watching a movie
>> and that's great but we really saw these
the potential for especially for mobile
tools for creativity to unlock you know
creation And so we really came up with
an entirely new OS for the courier which
was based around creativity. You know we
got it pretty far but like you know
eventually it was it was kind of killed
in Microsoft efforts to consolidate all
of their operating systems around one.
That was kind of when they you know made
everything like Windows Phone 7 and
Windows 7
>> really made everything very similar.
>> The first attempt at going ARM.
Yeah.
>> Your perspective then looking back on
that, do you see that as a work that you
were doing there had it kept like had
the world around it not changed so much
within Microsoft you were on the right
trajectory or were there things that
you're like now you're like ah we should
have thought through this in a different
way or in hindsight we could have maybe
gotten it over the finish line if we had
changed how we approached uh how we
approached building that. No, I mean I
think we definitely could have
shipped something that was very unique
and a very a very different perspective.
I mean I've even gone back and watched
like it leaked you know this whole
project leaked.
>> Oh yeah yeah I'm very aware.
>> That's why everybody knows about it
which is kind of a blessing honestly.
>> I did not leak it. Let me say that
legally for the record.
>> On the record. Yeah.
>> But it did leak. So there's videos and I
still think it presents a kind of vision
for how we could use software that is
still different. Some of that has been
implemented by iPad OS. You know, they
have a pencil now and they have like
some of the ideas of multitasking and
and an operating system that really
supports creativity like moving things
back and forth between applications and
stuff like that. We, you know, we tried
to put those sort of creative principles
at the forefront of an operating system.
I'm still excited about something like
that and not sure that we fully seen it
realized yet. So, in some ways, maybe it
was ahead of its time. Maybe it was
like, you know, just speaking to a
certain audience that a lot of
technology just wasn't interested in for
the longest time. I'd like to think that
if we were to like like someone could
still make that type of not exactly like
that obviously they'd make something
very different but in a way speak to
that audience. Yeah. And and and sort of
try and unlock
>> creativity
rather than pure consumption on these
devices. I mean, it's sort of my
complaint even with new platforms like
Vision OS, which are amazing
technically, but still feel very
consumptionoriented from the get- go. I
yearn for these things to be like these
great tools. I'm a creator and that's
>> the sort of thing that speaks to me and
that's what spoke to me about the early
Macintosh and Apple 2 and early
computers were these things as these
like amazing creative tools that could
unlock so much human creativity and
potential.
>> Are there ideas from that that you still
haven't seen implemented on iPad OS or
or across Android? And in particular,
you know, with the rumored iPhone Fold
coming out where theoretically more and
more people will have a wider
potentially creative canvas to play
with, you know, in their pocket.
>> Are there ideas from the things you were
developing or at least thinking about in
that era that you'd
>> think would be interesting to see both
at the OS level, but even at the like
developer level? There are a lot of
people with interesting ideas like I
mean there have been a lot of different
kind of conceptual takes at
reinvisioning the operating system right
like Jason Juan's Mercury OS and things
like that that I think just present
these very interesting alternative paths
right that we could have taken or could
speak to us in different ways and I
think it just gets you thinking very
differently about what could be but I
mean one yeah to call one thing out is
like we in creativ ity. It's very much
about moving things back and forth,
right? You're often mixing and matching
different things, right? Taking
something an asset over here and
bringing it into an application over
here to work on it and then bringing it
back over here. And like modern
operating systems, particularly like iOS
and iPad OS, they're just not
architected that way, right? They're
silos, right? And there good reasons to
make them silos, good like security and
privacy reasons for that. But it does
hurt this idea that of you know the
creator who just wants to move things
around very fluidly. Right.
>> I think that's where infinite canvas
tools like Figma or Sketch
>> Yeah.
>> have become really good at that because
while there are designers out there that
I'm sure keep their canvas very very
tightly constrained. In fact, at big
companies, you see like all these
systems built around it. But I feel like
the best work when I look at somebody's
Figma file from somebody who's really
good.
>> Mhm.
>> It's complete chaos because you're just
like option dragging and creating copy
over here and then you grab a piece from
over there. And the fact that copy and
paste works across everything, you do
end up in this sort of very dynamic,
fluid throwing stuff. It's like a messy
table. But that's where I feel like a
lot of the best creativity kind of comes
off.
>> Yeah. I mean, think of how much weight
they're just a few little tools that we
have and how much they carry like copy
paste operating system level kind of
copy paste. Also, screenshots like think
of how much people use screenshots. They
were not really intended to be used in
this way, but it's the only way to like
capture exactly what you're seeing in
one place and bringing it over to
another place in a very portable way,
right? And so, you know, we were
envisioning a lot of this sort of stuff
like in a very kind of fluid creative
focused way. Like how could you make
more of these like operating system
level tools and actions that can really
facilitate this kind of very free form
way of working rather than workflow
where you're going from A to B to C.
Much more free form. You can just mix
and match and not have to worry about
the walls of applications. Right.
>> Ah, that's cool. So the the Corer never
did see the light of day, but a portable
device from, you know, a different
company did, and the iPhone came out and
became this massive thing. Did you jump
on that right away? It sounds like
before this time, you hadn't been in
sort of just application world. You'd
been at sort of broader level. When the
iPhone came out, did you immediately get
excited and start building apps or what
was your sort of story of getting into
that?
>> I was very excited about the iPhone. And
I didn't start building applications
actually until the iPad came out. The
first app I built was an app called
paper, a drawing app. It was honestly
built on a lot of the understanding that
we sort of built up through working on
courier. And yeah, a lot of those same
principles around like free form
creation and creativity, although now it
had to be scaled from an operating
system down to just a single app. But it
was it was great. It really kind of
shocked us when it came out because to
us these were just ideas that we'd sort
of been living with for years and then
when it came out it kind of blew up
overnight and really had this overnight
success that really kind of caught us
off guard a little bit to be honest.
>> And the original business model was was
it free or was it paid up front? I
remember thinking of it as this like
tool that everybody's excited about and
less of like it's a business.
>> Is that how you were thinking about it?
No, I mean it was free. So it was
actually a new model at the time, new
for for like productivity apps, but it
was more common in gaming, which was
free with inapp purchases. So Apple
didn't have subscriptions at the time.
This was 2012 when it came out.
>> Yeah. Or at least when they did, it
wasn't allowed for anybody except for
specific types of apps.
>> Yeah. It was really just common in
gaming at the time to have free with
inapp purchases as the kind of business
model. But we I mean even back then we
just knew that when you looked at the
numbers you just got so many more
downloads, so many more people coming in
up front if it was free. And we wanted
people to come in and try it because
this was something new. We knew that
once they tried the ink and they felt
it, that's when people became convinced.
And I mean back then we get crazy like
high conversion numbers too because
these were people on the iPad and they
were looking for a reason why they
bought the iPad to some extent, right?
>> Some way to justify it.
>> And this was like something that was
unique to iPad
>> and and felt native on the iPad. I think
it was one of those early like native
iPad feeling apps.
>> And what was the the main pitch for
paper then? You know, it was like a
drawing creative app, but like how did
that differ from the other ones that are
out there? And this is pre- pencil, too,
right? Apple Pencil.
>> Yeah, this is pre-Apple Pencil. Pre-53
pencil, too, cuz we ended up making our
own stylus before the the Apple Pencil
came out.
>> Was that with the original app launch or
was that later?
>> That was about a year later.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah, we came out with the 53 pencil
and Yeah. So, what was the pitch? It was
it was really this is your digital
sketchbook, right? It's like if you have
a moles skin that you love to sketch out
and capture your ideas, this is our
version of it. And yeah, we weren't the
first. There were other drawing tools
out there. But I think we were one of
the first to try and envision it like
reinvision the navigation, the tools,
the ink, everything about it in the lens
of like someone who's creative. Like for
example, most note-taking apps back then
or sketch sketching apps back then, if
you wanted to capture something, you had
to like hit start a new page,
>> title my document, and then start
drawing. And we're like, at that point,
whatever idea you had in the moment is
gone or you've gotten distracted by
something else, right? So, we knew that
our competition was a sheet of paper or
a napkin or something, right? It's
something that quick. So, we made it
super simple. You didn't have to title
your documents. There were no documents,
right? It was just pages within this
three-dimensional journal. So, we built
it all in 3D. Everything was very
gestal, so you could get around very
quickly and very naturally. Everything
was spatially oriented because a lot of
people who like to sketch are very
spatially oriented people. And then we
spent a lot of time on the inks. You
know, we actually made them. We only had
a few inks. A lot of people had, you
know, infinitely customizable pens and
inks and brushes and things like that.
The problem is like it's very difficult
to find the few values on those sliders
that actually look good together. So, we
said, "Look, let's just find the sliders
that work, and then we'll open up a
dimension of expression through
acceleration and speed and eventually
things like pressure and whatnot that
let you do more and be more expressive
with it and get different aesthetics
from it, but let's not, you know,
bombard you with tons of sliders and
things like that." So, I think it really
appealed to people who just wanted
something that just worked and looked
good right out of the gate and sort of
worked the way that they thought.
>> And then you said a year into that is
when you came out with a piece of
hardware to go with it, right? And that
was the 53 pen,
>> right? And that was in the works even
from the get-go. That was part of the
bigger vision. What we knew that having
a tool in your hand was going to be very
important because just drawing with your
finger is not great. And there's just a
certain level of precision that you can
get from your hands and your fingers,
right? It's great for navigating. I
mean, it was the right sort of, you
know, Steve Jobs, of course, famously
yucked the uh the stylus when he
launched the iPhone. And it's great for
getting around and consuming, but when
you need to make something, you need a
level of precision. There's a reason
that we have tools all around us, right?
Like scissors and pencils. And I'm very
into woodworking, so I love tools,
right? And we knew that that was a very
critical part to it. And so from the
get-go, we were designing like an active
stylus that would we were some of the
first to do things like pressure
sensitivity. You could flip it around
and erase with the back side of the
pencil. things like that, you know, that
were quite innovative at the time helped
set up, you know, Apple for what they
ended up doing with pencil.
>> Paper is not currently still a running
concern, right? So, what happened there?
>> Yeah. Not for me. It is still in the app
store.
>> Oh, it is. Okay.
>> Yeah. Yeah. It still has millions of
users. I mean, it's still still heavily
used. What happened there is we, you
know, this was 2012. We were part of the
early kind of app craze, right? If you
remember, everyone was building apps,
you know, and we kind of rode some of
that excitement. Some of it we needed,
you know, so we we raised money. We went
the VC route and raised a lot of money.
We needed the money to do the hardware
to be honest. You can't just bootstrap,
>> especially with hardware. Yeah.
>> Yeah. It's just there's a lot of very
real costs there. So, we went that route
and the company grew for a while and
then you kind of reach a point where you
realize, well, this is sort of about how
big the company's going to get. And it
was clear that we weren't on the
trajectory to become the next
multi-billion dollar company, but that's
what the VCs and investors are investing
in. So, you know, it's no surprise to
anyone who's sort of ridden this ride,
which is most people who've raised money
don't have that billion dollar outcome.
You're sort of put in a tough position
to figure out what to do. And we ended
up selling the company to Wi Transfer.
They're a European version of Dropbox
essentially, right?
>> Which was acquired by Bending Spoons, I
think.
>> And then, yeah, recently they were they
were acquired by Bending Spoons. So I
worked for we transfer then for a little
while for about 2 years leading some
design and product teams there and then
just started to get that itch again of
like well I kind of want to do
something. I feel like I have a little
bit more to say in the world of apps.
>> And is that the beginning of the origin
story for not boring apps then?
>> It is. Yeah. I mean to tell it a little
bit a little bit more deeply is I didn't
really know what I wanted to do next
honestly. I just left we transfer and
and was sort of looking around and I
stumbled on the artist John Baldesari.
He's uh Yeah. So,
>> I only know I I say that I make that
face as if I know who he is other than
because of your original blog post uh
>> whenever you kind of blew on the scene
and that was that's part of the story,
right, for
>> I never know how many folks don't cuz
he's he's like, you know, one of the
biggest names in the in the art world.
certainly the experimental art world but
yeah not so well known among designers
and technologists but he you know for
the first half of his life he was very
much just a kind of he was an art
student and then a very kind of mediocre
landscape painter that's what he called
it himself right he called himself a
mediocre landscape painter until he was
almost 40 so like midcareer when most
people think you know your art career is
over he took all of his paintings, his
entire body of work that he'd done over
decades and decades, and he just burned
it all, lit it all on fire. And in that
moment, like vowed to never make any
more boring art. And that he wrote that
statement out over and over again,
thousands of times while videoing it to
just he just said, "I will not make any
more boring art. I will not make any
more boring art." you know, over and
over again in a very kind of performance
art way, right? It was a very this was
like the early years of experimental art
and performance art and things like that
and then went on to like do some of the
most profound art that has really
influenced a whole new generation since
then. And you know I it's funny cuz I
was reaching kind of that same point in
my life you know approaching 40
and that just really struck me and it I
felt like you know that's a good
sometimes there's just like a good very
simple heruristics right if you can just
say I will not make any more boring
software that might lead to some good
outcomes right and that was that was
really it it was like let's just what
does not boring software look like did
Do you feel like what you had been doing
before that was boring software though?
Cuz at least in our discussion so far,
it felt like a lot of what you've been
doing has been you exploring new ideas
and pushing boundaries. It didn't seem
like you were on the sort of Figma JSON
viewer basically sidebar on the left
like standard kind of thing, right?
>> Yeah. And thankfully I'd had those
experiences, but you know, I had found
myself over the last like two or three
years leading up to this slipping more
and more into the, you know, what was
fashionable at the time, which was
building your B2B SAS business.
Honestly, I had taken on a little bit
more of a product role rather than a
designer. So I was I was the one living
in Amplitude all the time, looking at
the metrics every Yeah. Okay. seeing
where we're moving and and what
>> I can see the existential crisis
growing. Uh
>> yeah, it was I mean I was sort of
filling a gap that needed to be filled
at the time, you know, that's what you
do when you're at a startup, especially
one that just is struggling and needs
some needs some attention. So I was
doing what needed to be done, but it
wasn't really the thing that was feeding
the soul, right? That was important for
me. I think that moment and Baldesari's
words there was important to just kind
of remember like oh this is why I got
into design and it led me into apps
which is strange cuz in 2020
like in building an app business was not
at the top of anyone's like dream.
>> No, that was definitely a lull in the
like cool factor.
>> Exactly. It's gotten more fashionable
recently, but it was very much out of
fashion at the time, and everyone,
>> ironically, the moment that I got into
it, uh, as well.
>> Oh, there you go. Perfect.
>> But maybe that's a sign that it had lost
its cool is now I'm here. Yeah. Well,
it's, you know, it's it I've it's so
funny cuz I I just found that often
times the things that I've done that
have had the most staying power or
resonated the most have often been these
very uncool things. Like whenever you
try to be do something cool or like of
the moment, it just doesn't really go
anywhere or it flubs. But doing these
very uncool things has proven to play
out well for me at least. And so that
was one of those moments where it was
very like no one else is starting an app
business. Should we really do this? You
know, okay, you make that choice. What's
the thesis then? Other than not boring
because you know experimental art uh
while can change the world isn't
necessarily a business the same way. And
like your last business you had to raise
money and all that. Did you have a
thesis this time for things you wanted
to do different or how you were going to
build this or was it okay if it just
made a small dent in the universe in
terms of the design world but didn't
give you a foundation for this is can
sustain me a lot of it came out of
lessons from 53 my prior company
and in hindsight I'd realized that we
had a great small business with paper
but we just hadn't built the business.
We hadn't built the incentives, right?
We hadn't built the company in a way to
support that, right? We we raised money.
We took certain paths that made that.
And so, some of it was just recognizing
that, well, you can have a true like
sustainable small business where you can
do interesting work
and support that through a business if
you build it correctly and you kind of
incentivize yourself to do the things
that you want to do. And so, we were
very deliberate. And I say we, it's me
and my partner. There two of us. There's
still two of us. And we were very
>> step one, right, in making it okay to
stay small is not having, you know, a
large a company with a lot of headcount
that you have to feed.
>> Yeah. You know, we both had been through
the startup cycles. He's been through it
twice. I've been through it once where
you start a company, you scale it to
dozens or hundred plus people, and then
you sell it. That kind of thing. And
it's funny because when we got together
again, we just love working together.
And when we got together, we were like,
you know, the best like our favorite
time at the company was really when it
was just you and your co-founder sitting
around a kitchen table making stuff.
And what if you could build a company
that was just that, right? And if you
just like scaled, you know, if you just
do the uncool thing and ignore what
everyone is saying about you got to
scale and that's, you know, you got to
like raise money and like that's how
everyone gets attention now, right? And
just like stay small, you know, you can
build a company where you can do the
things that you want to do and hopefully
motivates you to do the types of things
that you want to do. So even the way
that we chose to monetize the work that
we do was very intentional in terms of
trying to incentivize us to do what we
want to do.
>> And was that thinking happening
pre even building apps like how you're
going to monetize?
>> Yeah, it was part of it. I mean, yeah,
you asked about the thesis and so I
didn't really address that, but the idea
was it was really a thought experiment.
We honestly I wasn't expecting it to be
a business. It was meant to be a thought
experiment. And the experiment being can
you build truly design differentiated
software? And that sounds so simple
because we all think design is what
differentiates good software from bad
software. But the more you dig, the more
you realize, well really it's because it
has this feature.
>> Yeah.
>> The value. We talk about this a lot, you
know, at Revenue Cat where I work. It's
like people pay for value at the end of
the day. And it's not that design can't
be value, but boy is that a
significantly harder cell. And just to
kind of bury or not bury the lead,
whatever the phrase is to to pull ahead
here, the apps you've made are a
calculator, a timer, a weather app. And
so, and each of these, you can correct
me if I'm wrong, but other than maybe
the camera, that one's a little
different, but none of them are things
that you could pitch on an elevator. And
somebody goes, "Oh, that's interesting."
Because I've been doing this a while and
talked to a lot of developers and when
somebody says, "Oh, the reason is
because it's beautiful design and it
feels really good." You kind of roll
your eyes cuz you're like, "Okay, yeah."
Like everybody says that, right? So
actually differentiating on design is I
can't even think of almost any like app
businesses really aside from I think
maybe you that that is really that is it
that's kind of the main pitch. It always
struck me as weird because again I'm
someone who came from the graphic design
world and doing physical things and it's
not weird in everything else
>> like Moles skins are very popular and
you can go pay way less money for one
just as valuable and has just as many
good features.
>> Exactly. It's you're not picking in your
notebook based on features. You're not
picking like your sofa based on its
features. Right. Like
>> I mean sometimes you are like that is a
thing in physical design also.
>> Yeah. Yeah. It's not it's not devoid of
it but yeah I mean or cars you know I
mean yeah like there are some feature
differences but like they're kind of
minor and we have strong opinions about
brand and design and the aesthetics of
cars, right? Even if you don't think
you're an aesthetically oriented person,
I guarantee you have opinions about how
you wear, what you drive, what you
choose to do with your free time, things
like that, right? Like you have opinions
about things like this. I think those
are valuable things. And increasingly,
as much as like people want to believe
that I don't know, there's there's this
constant belief I feel like that people
have that that we're going to be more
off our screens in the future or
something or like the new technologies
means we're not going to be using
technology. I don't know. It's this
forever kind of lie that technology
likes to sell us, right? That like the
new device is going to make us more
present by putting
>> you strap a computer to your wrist,
you'll use your computer in your pocket
less. Exactly. Right. Or, oh well, let's
just what we really need to do is put
the computer on the eyes. Right now
you'll be present.
>> Now you'll be free.
>> Exactly. And so maybe it's fatalist of
me, but like I kind of just embrace
that. I think we're going to be spending
a lot more time in software, you know,
in whatever form that takes. And I don't
see that as a bad thing. I think
software is great and beautiful and it
can be what we want it to be. It's one
of the most flexible, most prolific, you
know, widest reaching mediums that we've
ever probably have ever created, right?
So, I love software and I think we're
going to live in increasingly more and
more of it. So, why not be shaping it
the way that we want to shape it? It
should reflect us, our individuality,
our aesthetics, our taste, and that kind
of thing. And then when you look at the
world of software and what people run on
their devices, it's largely the same,
right? Almost everyone is running the
same weather app, the same calculator.
It's weird. It's like imagine stepping
outside and 90% of people are wearing
the same exact outfit that you are,
right? Like that would be a cult. I
mean, so it's
>> I wanted to see that type of world,
right? You know, I'm curious how much of
the reason people make purchasing
decisions based on design has to do with
the really has to do with the experience
of using it versus the signaling it does
externally because I do think there is a
significant amount of money being made
purely based on design which is like
skins in video games, but that is users
making purchasing decisions that let
them signal to the outside world
something about themselves, express
themselves in some way.
>> Whereas for the most part, I think it's
true that like especially on your phone,
the software you use is extremely
intimate. Very few people are seeing
what you're using almost ever. And do
you think that that's a part of that?
Yeah, certainly a part of design is
brand and what it what it signals
outward, but also what often gets missed
when you talk about brand and outward
signaling is also how it sort of
reflects back on you. Like we often
choose things because they help us kind
of communicate who we think we are. You
know what I mean?
>> Or what we value.
>> Yeah.
>> Value might be premium feel and all this
stuff. But it's like it's externally
validated or like you can see it. Right.
>> Exactly. Right. what groceries you buy
and all these things. As much as they're
signals outward, they're also ways for
you to maybe try and understand who you
are, if that makes sense, and what
values you want to embody, right, and
live by and that kind of thing. So, I
think it definitely goes both ways. And
yeah, software for sure is often been a
very private thing. And so it often
doesn't have that outward signaling, but
I think it's still prevalent to to an
extent. And I think there's still a
space for this for like design oriented
software to again like help you figure
out what values you want to embody. And
maybe there is some outward signaling
too in some way with software or maybe
that's yet to be cracked, right, beyond
avatars and skins and things like that.
But so that might be part of it as well.
But I'm excited about that type of of
future where you know we can have a lot
of different voices
creating a lot of different types of
ideas that are expressed through
software. I love the idea of, you know,
the Italian artist Bruno Munari who was
a sculptor but writes a lot about design
and he writes about how we're sort of
constantly trying to find this balance
in life between the sort of like outward
material world and the inward moral
world. And design often helps become the
sort of bridge between that. And the
hope is that art can be brought into the
everyday, right? And so that art is not
just something that is in the galleries
or is in these very like controlled
moments in our life, but it's something
that we can live with, right? And so the
artist perspective helps us reflect on
our own perspective and the material can
can sort of like, you know, coexist with
the moral and we can live every day
among art, right? And so I love that
idea of bringing art into the everyday
where we can experience that. You can
pop open your weather app and you can
experience hopefully a little moment of
like artistic expression that maybe in
some way helps shape your view for the
day. You know that's that's you know
that's a dream at least.
>> So let's let's actually get into the
apps then. You've made this choice. you
you wanted to and I don't think we said
but the monetization method for these is
a subscription that unlocks things
within each app and then there's also I
think even from the very beginning you
had like a group subscription that kind
of captures all of the not boring not
boring apps right
>> when you launched this is my memory and
correct me if I'm wrong but my memory is
you started I think you didn't even
release the apps immediately you wrote
your I promise I won't make boring
software anymore our blog post which
we'll link in the description. It's
excellent. Like very worth reading
definitely.
>> But then following up on that, you
released I think a set of apps. It
wasn't just one app right at the
beginning. And
>> I think it I'll let you say which ones
it was, but it was it was more of these
like simple utility tools that everybody
uses apps, right?
>> Yep. Yeah. So we released weather,
calculator, and timer.
And yeah, we released three of those.
You could get them individually or you
could get the full collection of of
apps.
>> It's a subscription. And with weather,
it's a little easier. You can say like
you can get premium data sources along
with it. But for the other apps, pretty
much what you were unlocking was like
making it look different, right? There's
kind of different styles, different app
icons, that kind of thing.
>> Yeah. For the most part, you were
unlocking skins in those early apps. And
so yeah, and we were regularly, you
know, every few months we would push out
a new skin, sometimes collaborations
with artists that we that we like. So
that was kind of the idea. But the way
that we looked at it and the way that we
tried to position and still do to an
extent the subscription is it's a little
bit almost like a patron model, you
know, where like it's really fueling the
work that we do and we try and come out
with a new app every year. So we've come
out, it's been 5 years now, we have six
apps out and every year we come out with
a new one. And if you're part of that,
if you're one of the patrons, you just
get the new app, right? you get it for
free. We're not charging you another X
dollars on top of it. And the other
thing that we decided early on is like
we're going to lock your price in. The
people who paid like early on in that
first batch, they're still getting a
great price now. So if they're still
around, you know, we've locked in that
price for them. And so they just every
year get a new app that they get to add
on top. So that's kind of how we justify
the ongoing. Of course, there are like
ongoing expenses with things like
weather data, which is a lot more
expensive than a lot of people realize,
and there's like maintenance costs and
stuff like that that helps it, but we
kind of see it in that way. We try not
to justify it in terms of like x many
features and things like that. It's
more, you know, what you pay for is this
ongoing effort to try and build
interesting apps, you know, and if
you're interested in following along in
the work that we do, it's the best way
to support us just by buying our
subscription, our membership plan. And
yeah, cuz like normally, you know,
advice would be don't make that the
value proposition cuz if people are
coming to your app for a specific value
and the thing you lock away is the thing
that is nice, but people don't care that
much about like alternate app icons or
skins, you're not going to get many
people to do it. But like like you said,
your whole thesis here is that really it
is differentiating on design. And that
last bit, it was interesting to hear you
say that cuz I feel like for me and for
a lot of people in my area, that's more
of the thing is almost supporting the
work, the artistic work, and coming up
with ideas and inspiring people or
whatever. And that yeah, it is like a
patronage versus I'm getting this out of
it. Obviously, you are getting something
out of it, but the free versions of a
lot of these are are pretty good. So,
did that work?
>> Yeah. Well, even the first so the first
plans that we launched, there's one tier
which was essentially you unlock all the
apps. It was like, you know, you get
everything, right? We offered another
tier above that that we literally called
the patron plan that was more expensive.
I mean, it was five times as expensive
and you didn't really get anything new.
We send people a gift, like a physical
gift, but it was really just about
supporting us. And it was shocking how
many people went for that plan, right?
And that was kind of the moment that we
realized, oh yeah, this is a little bit
of a different business model, right?
Like we're not selling or a different
proposition. We're not selling features
here. like people want to see this work
and see us maybe as you know the knights
fighting this battle against boring
software and they want to fund this
effort and so we've ever since then
we've been leaning into that because
honestly I think that's what we are and
it also allows us to do the type of work
that we want to do so we're not trying
to chase features that are going to
unlock some like new audience for us or
that we think are gonna suddenly bump up
our conversion rates because we've added
these new features and it's more on par
with the other apps, that kind of thing.
Well, and even if you were thinking that
cynically, because of what the value
proposition is, the incentives that
you've built are to actually do things
that are inspiring and feeding the
narrative at least that you're doing
new, interesting, creative things that
can help inspire other people versus
like an innovative feature. Cuz that can
be just as innovative, but it's a very
different thing. And at least it appears
that it sends you down a route where
you're not chasing
really deep crazy new feature work. And
it's more like how can we take a
different design approach to a very
well-traddened problem space that again
you couldn't really pitch in an elevator
because it's like how is this calcul
like what does this calculator do that
other calculators don't? And it's like
there isn't really an answer at all for
that. Right? There aren't many folks in
the software space that do this and so
maybe it's just
I don't know maybe it's just a kind of
unnatural too much confidence or
something but you know my thinking was
always like if we just do what we want
to do there's got to be somebody out
there who's going to like resonate with
it right and be interested in it and I
don't know how big that business is
going to be but guess what there's just
two of us it doesn't have to that big.
>> Exactly.
>> And that's the other key piece is like
we kept everything very small.
Thankfully, we've been in tech long
enough and had some, you know, some
success along the way that we can afford
ourselves that opportunity to watch it
grow, right? Cuz, you know, it's not a
big business like right out of the gate.
But I think there was just some of that
confidence that like if we just do what
we want to do, we will attract the right
people and we'll see what business is
there. And if there is no business
there,
oh well, maybe we'll do something else,
right? You know, the biggest fear was
like getting trapped in a business that
you didn't want to run. And I see that
happen with so many founders. And so
very very much from the get-go, we
thought of what we wanted to build and
how we wanted to build and how we wanted
to work. So even the fact that we come
out with a new app every year, like
that's just kind of an expectation now.
And so in doing that, we can't go back
and like work on calculator V3 or
something, right? I mean, what are we
gonna add? Like, we could add a ton of
new features to it, but I prefer to say
like this is the calculator that we
made.
>> Yeah. It's a complete product.
>> Yeah. And it's complete and it does its
job really well. We're not going to
change it on you. It's not going to
suddenly like have a chatbot in the
corner, right? It's like it's just what
it is. And we'll keep updating it,
making sure that it works on all the OS
versions. Maybe we'll add tiny hooks
here and there for whatever new things
come out like widgets or dynamic island
stuff like that. But we're not going to
dramatically change it. And that pushes
us on this path to making new apps,
right? And then that happens to align
with the sort of thing that we're
excited about, which is making and
reinvisioning old software in new ways,
right? And putting our own spin on it.
So things like the camera app was a
great example of that sort of playing
out, right? Where we had a chance to
really reinvision what we thought a
camera should be.
>> Yeah. And I want to get into the camera
app here in a second, but like going
back or everything leading up to the
camera app, it feels like your kind of
design language is pretty consistent
between all of them, which is kind of
like we've said, very simplified, not
overdone on features or anything like
that. But then in particular,
it's not about, you know, it being a iOS
app or a whatever. It's its own language
which is very focused on a lot of 3D
gestural animations. They feel like
games. One of the really big ones is the
sound design and your choice to which I
think a lot of apps could not never get
away with. But you play the sound even
if the mute switch is on, which is
something that makes total sense when
the whole point of it is to experience
something that you're not experiencing
elsewhere. But if anybody else did that,
they would get destroyed uh in reviews
and everything, right? Because people
get really upset at that. But whenever
you go into your calculator app or
weather app, that's almost why you're
there, right? Is to experience this
thing. Is that how you were thinking
about it or or do you disagree and
you're like, "No, everybody should be
pushing more and more sound design that
your phone is always making sounds." I
think sound is sound design
is just not done very well to I mean
>> no it's not prioritized almost by
anybody
>> it's almost nobody does it everyone's
kind of written it off and said
everybody mutes their phones anyways and
nobody wants to you know that's for the
kids websites or apps or something right
yeah sound is a huge part of video games
and you alluded to it but video games
were a huge inspiration for me
throughout my career
and long wanted to inject more of video
game design into the software I made.
And so Not Boring has really been a
vehicle for that. So everything that we
do is in a 3D space, a 3D engine, and we
3D model everything, you know, and we
just think it brings a certain like
tactility and dimensionality and sort of
sense of physical space that just really
speaks to the way that I like to use
software and hearkens back to I think
for a lot of us what is like probably
our most connected that we ever felt to
software was often video games. honestly
like we grew up on video games, you
know, and and some of the deepest
experiences that we've had have been
with video games now. And so sound is a
huge part of that. And I think a lot of
people just don't do it well. Honestly,
I wrote a whole article on this trying
to give away our secrets so that other
people could do it well. And I am
starting to see more people doing it,
which is great. And we even literally
gave away sound kits of buttons and
things like that. But just for example,
one small thing is normally what
everybody does when they have, let's say
they put a click or something on a
button tap,
they have one click file, one like sound
file, and it just plays the same one
over and over and over. And guess what?
Like no button ever sounds exactly the
same. Like why does it sound so great to
like listen to someone like typing on an
old clicketity clacky keyboard, right?
like that can sound wonderful but not
when you move it digital. It's because
of all the variation, right? When you
hit a physical button, it hits
differently every time, right? And this
is a thing that is used in gaming
because gaming has the same problem. You
might need to punch over and over
repeatedly in a row and you don't want
>> or footsteps. That's a common one.
>> Footsteps. Yeah. Or like background
music is a thing. Like how do you keep
that interesting and kind of changing
over time? And so there are all these
techniques. And so one of them in video
games and one of them is just don't have
one sound file, have a dozen sound files
for that same button click that are all
slightly different and suddenly it
doesn't sound as grading anymore to us.
And so there's like a dozen or so tricks
like that that we all we just gave away
for others to use because I would love
to hear more sounds. You know, I'm
someone who likes to hear sounds in
software and I think it just really amps
up the experience that you have. And
then the flip sort of corlary to sound
is haptics. And again, a lot of people I
think don't use haptics nearly enough.
You can make your own custom haptics in
iOS. Literally like your own custom
haptic patterns,
>> right? So everything feels a little
different.
>> Yeah. And you can use the defaults.
There's some good defaults, but
literally you can make your own haptics
that feel, you know, feel weighty or
feel like an explosion or things like
that. And again, it doesn't take much.
Honestly, just takes working with a
sound designer. And, you know, I highly
recommend that for anyone who's building
apps. Consider sound. I mean, it's a
great way to amplify your experience
that really doesn't add much overhead or
complexity to the app itself. it's just,
you know, it's built in or it doesn't
add it to the experience, right? It's
it's sort of like layered on on top.
>> Yeah. I think the trick in that
particular case, but maybe in a lot of
things that you do is,
you know, you're working in a game
engine and your users are expecting a
different kind of experience explicitly.
Whereas most people making like
productivity software especially there
is an expectation of things fitting
within the stand cuz you're not building
an operating system. You're building
something that lives inside of an
operating system and there is an
expectation for most users that things
feel and look similar in certain ways.
So like you are completely ignoring the
whole liquid glass thing because that
defeats the purpose of the app, right?
you're the whole point is that it's this
unique interesting experience. And so,
not only are you able to do sound
effects that that play even when the
mute switch is on, but you can have the
visuals when you tap something in your
app have a weight to it's like a punch
in a video game. It's like things crash
or move or skip frames, I'm guessing
anyway, to have this feeling of like
this was an expensive action. This is a
light, thin action. And so the sound,
the haptics, the visuals, you can do all
this stuff in your app that I at least
don't feel the permission to do, not
just from the company I'm working for,
but from users. Does that make sense?
Like
>> No, I mean it does, but
>> it's a weird balancing thing that I feel
like you've almost built a business
where you are allowed or almost have to
now ignore in a way that it does. It
feels like everybody else lives on a
different platform that they kind of
have to live within or different
constraints maybe.
>> Yeah, maybe maybe I'm being too
optimistic, but I think there's room for
it. You know, I mean, the way that we do
have some liquid glass. The way that we
see it is like we exist within we're not
blind that we, you know, we exist within
an operating system. And so we don't
reinvent everything. We don't reinvent
the menus and share sheets. I guess
that's true. And so we we see it as a
bit of a kind of like, you know, they're
providing a foundation and we're
building something on top of that. And
so we can build our own perspective, but
it has to kind of work with the Apple
language as well, right? And so we see
that really as more of a collaboration
really rather than us just doing our own
cuz some video games do it where they
really just like, hey, it's full screen,
you know, it's built in Unity.
>> Yeah, video games are great. The menus
can be extremely obtuse.
>> Um,
>> exactly.
>> But it works thing.
>> You're in it and then like you learn
that that design language, but like you
couldn't do that in a calculator app
because people don't live in their
calculator app. They're bouncing there
from somewhere else and they need this
sort of familiarity.
>> Yeah. And they don't want to wait 10
seconds for Unity to boot up either.
That's the other thing I'm curious about
is
>> because you lean so hard into video game
engines. Is that a power concern? I
mean, most of your apps you're not like
sitting in for a really long time, so
maybe not, but is that something that
you're you're always thinking about or
again, is it you're allowed to make
different trade-offs than a typical
productivity app? And so it
>> Yeah. So part of it is is yeah, we make
utility apps that you're often in and
out of. You're not scrolling an endless
feed in our apps. you're intended to
kind of go into the calculator and pop
out, but then also we take it very
seriously perf and and battery usage and
things like that and startup time. So,
we use Apple's 3D game engine called
SceneKit
and it can be quite performant and so it
just depends on how you use it and what
things you use. We also don't push it
like you can you can try and push it to
get very like photorealistic things. We
actually embrace a little bit more of
like a PS1 era.
>> Yeah. It's very polygon low poly kind
of.
>> Exactly. Very low poly. I've gotten very
good now at like rendering or modeling
very low poly models. We very much think
about all those things how we can make
it very performant. Actually, our camera
app, I've tested it against other camera
apps, and we launch faster than all the
other camera apps, minus Apple's like
default camera app, which you know,
granted, they probably have some
>> special sauce. They can like start
booting up the camera before the app is
even like fully zoomed open, but we can
boot up faster than any other camera
app. And so, it's not the 3D, you know,
the 3D stuff. You can actually optimize
that quite a bit. And given that we're
doing like PS1 level graphics, I mean,
the GPUs on these modern devices and
modern phones is way past what PS1 could
ever do, right? So, they're very
performant actually. Now, yeah, if you
leave it open for a long time, like a
camera app, I mean, any camera app, you
leave it open for a long time, it's
going to start eating up the battery,
right? So, there's some element of that,
but we're very conscious of it. We're
very performanceoriented
when we think about how we build our
apps because we know that people need to
use them regularly and yeah they don't
want to have to make that sacrifice
right so we try and do everything that
we can so they don't have to so they can
get something beautiful and I mean
there's so many like poorly built apps
out there that they just eat up battery
and you're like what are you even doing
with all this juice right like it's it's
not rendering anything interesting or
there's some background processes you
whatever it's doing. So, we we try and
be very conscious of that. Yeah.
>> So, you mentioned the camera app and we
Yeah, we have to talk about that because
quite frankly, for me, I've always liked
all of your apps as like toys or
experiments to play with, but I'm
usually looking for more features or
whatever. And the camera app in
particular is one that I've found
extremely interesting. And I think
you're pushing further than you've
pushed any of your other ones. Maybe you
would disagree, but it feels like
there's more like
interesting under the hood things
happening there and certainly more value
in the what do you get whenever you
subscribe than normal. So, I'm curious
like
>> what led you to making a camera app in
the first place and what was the again
thesis behind how it's different than
everything else other than just 3D
graphics?
>> Yeah, we started on the camera app
about 3 years prior to releasing it. So
it was in the works for a while and it
was really just you know I again coming
from a film making background and my
partner being very interested in
photography as well and he's one of the
best graphics engineers out there. So
it's it was always just a an interest
for us. We were just kind of exploring
different things that you know what
could you do with a camera. We sort of
went on a very like ciruitous route
trying to figure out what this camera
app could be. So we'd pick it up for a
month or two and try some things with a
new idea and then abandon it and then
and we did that off.
>> Was the starting point just
>> not camera what is that like is that
okay? So the idea was let what is a
camera app from us look like?
>> Exactly. And we go through these
journeys. It's not very linear, right?
And I think that's just how the creative
process is. Like you're trying to figure
out what is at the core of this thing
and what makes it interesting. And we
were like exploring all sorts of
different things. Okay. Could we do like
3D photography, right? And then you can
look at your photos in 3D almost like
and then Apple came out with their sort
of spatial photos and things like that.
So we were looking at all these
different like interesting ways that we
could make it better. And then
eventually we realized like you know
what
we make basic apps
we just improve the experience of basic
apps right like we make a great weather
app feel great like something that you
want to open. So let's not try and like
reinvent too much what a camera app can
be and do but let's just reinvent what
the experience of using a camera app can
be. We started there and we started
thinking, well, what if, you know, we
use 3D in all of our apps, but for the
most part, the controls are actually on
like a Swift UI or UI kit layer that
sits above the 3D. Like you can spin the
3D or do a few basic things with it, but
like once you need to get into
>> much more static, you're not throwing
things around or
>> spinning things. Yeah. So, but this was
like what if we actually built all the
controls in 3D? And then it led us down
this path of making a very like tactile
camera where the sliders and the dials
and the buttons and everything are
actually in 3D. When you press on them,
they tilt based on where you press,
right? You can feel the haptics and hear
the sounds. And like we just thought
like let's just take that as far as we
can and just make that experience of
holding the app in your hands as good as
possible. And we just found ourselves
loving how the thing felt. And then it
was like well how did how are these
photos need to look right? like and this
is a couple years ago now and it's only
gotten worse since I would say where
photography on the phones has become
very processed right and I would say
very overprocessed
in that a lot of the photos that you
take like now we're having these debates
like is it even a real photo if you're
doing these like multiframe you know
exposure compensation and composits
right where you're pulling together the
sky from one photo which which is
underexposed and the foreground which is
overexposed and then melding them
together. And then sometimes you get
weirdness when you try and do that
especially when things are
>> the camera app's clear goal is capturing
a memory the way that you see it and
remember seeing it more than anything
else. Right.
>> Well, the way I like to say it is the
default camera apps. It's not just
Apple, it's Google, it's it's everyone,
right? Their goal is to make sure that
you never take a bad photo,
but I think the result is that you never
can really take a great one. You know,
>> I hear that a lot. It's not about never
taking a bad photo. It's about
never missing the moment you're trying
to capture. If you're if you're taking a
picture of people at night, it's better
to be overexposed
with all the weird night things and just
be noisy or oversharpened as hell. But
like memory preserved, like that's the
point. And same if you take a picture of
a car going by because it looks funny or
whatever. Like you're trying to capture
this memory. You're not trying to
capture a photograph with a capital P or
whatever. Like they're different goals.
Which is why contrast doesn't matter.
Cuz if your goal is to just make it look
like always be an okay photograph,
there's different decisions you could
make in terms of contrast and stuff to
make it look more photography. But I
think it's really way more about people
taking pictures of menus and memories of
all these people together and
everybody's exposed exactly the same
than it is about taking a picture that
you put on your wall the same way. Maybe
I'm wrong.
>> You're right in the sense that I think
there's a very like scientific there's
like a you know there's a version of
photography that's very scientific
that's like let's make sure that your
exposure histogram is perfect, right?
There's nothing clipped on the edges.
Everything's kind of in the middle. And
I think it I think it's true if you show
like two photos of like, hey, this one
has a blown out sky behind it and this
one has the sky that looks, you know,
correctly exposed or maybe the way that
you remember seeing it, like people are
going to choose that one, right? Just
like if you show an HDR photo versus an
SDR, they're people are like, well, that
HDR one looks a little like shinier,
right? But I actually think to me, it's
funny that you mentioned memories. To
me, it feels like it doesn't capture the
feeling of when I was there all that
well. You know what I mean? Like I feel
like it doesn't capture the moment that
that I remember feeling in a lot of
these photos. It's like it's technically
very accurate. Like everything's sharp
and exposed correctly. So, what we ended
up doing is we just strip all that out,
right? So, we I mean the beautiful thing
about Apple is they expose their raw
data, right? And so you can actually
take the raw data from a photo and build
your own pipeline. So we built our own
pipeline. We call it super raw because
Apple is pro raw, but it's still
processed quite a bit actually. So we're
like, well, what's more raw? Let's call
it super raw. And so and also I love
Super Nintendo and the whole Nintendo
idea of Super, right? So we said, let's
call it Super Raw. So it's we just take
all that out. And there are a couple
other apps that have done this, too. And
you can actually get a very beautiful
photo cuz the the cameras on these
devices have gotten so much better. You
know, this made a lot of sense back when
cameras were not as good. But like as as
the cameras and the sensors have gotten
better, it produces decent results. And
because it's raw, you get such a wide
range of values already. And the other
thing that we do is we let you actually
edit the raw data in the app. So you can
like shift the exposure or pull back the
highlights or push it up or you know
change the temperature after the fact
change the the L. So we apply LUTs as
well in real time so you can see them.
So that's like another cinematography
back to my film making era of like
applying LUTs to photos which is
becoming more common now too. It's not
the same as a filter because it's
applied to the raw data and so you can
get much more crazy like effects from
it, right? And that's how filmmakers get
like these wild effects. So we try and
model some of them after filmmakers we
like like Wes Anderson and things like
that. So So yeah, you can get just a
much more expressive range of photos and
it means you can get like blur and
noise. I mean, the odd thing is people
like Apple takes out the noise in their
photos and then people add it back in,
right? Because they want that grain
effect and we just say, "Well, just
don't take it out, right? Just shoot it
with the noise or the grain and embrace
it, right?" And so you can get blurry
photos or things like that. And so,
yeah, it's kind of embracing that idea
of photography as as a little bit more
of an expressive medium, I would say,
rather than like a documentation medium,
right? I've gone down this route many
times where I want to take my, you know,
my nice camera that I have right here
that's very small for a full-frame
camera, but unless it's out and I have
it on a on my strap, it's like I'm not
going to take most pictures with it. So
I've gone through many many photography
apps and you know since the kind of big
Fujifilm resurgence three or four years
ago, the film simulation app game is is
pretty big. And this is why I say the
camera app is is somewhat unique to me
compared to your other apps because the
utility of using it is actually like I
could I could pitch this to somebody on
an elevator and really pitch it to them
which is like there are quite a few apps
now that do the sort of film simulation
thing in app and a lot of them are
really good and a lot of them focus more
on film simulations. I think one
interesting thing about your simulations
is and now I understand why hearing you
say it is that it does seem more movie
film inspired and the fact that you can
bring LUTs in is kind of in that same
vein, right? But the thing that I think
not boring camera does extraordinarily
well is like Fujifilm. One of the big
reasons people talk about it so much is
the feel of turning dials and like
making it the way you want kind of in
camera. that I've not found a another
app that matches the ability to kind of
like there's a dial specifically for
switching between film simulations and
there's a dial for changing your
exposure level. Something about those
things. Maybe I wouldn't be able to
describe this cuz if I I'm hearing
myself say it out loud and now I'm like
I would roll my eyes at somebody saying
this, but it genuinely does capture that
feeling. Also, the fact that the preview
is not full screen. It's like inset.
You're not making the preview as big as
you possibly can.
>> And something about that does make it
feel very different
>> capturing with it compared to the camera
app or these other very very nice
professional camera apps that I also
use.
>> It's interesting you hear that cuz the
camera app was
>> I mean we've made like weather and
calculator and those they're a little
bit more utility.
camera app was our first my first like
creative app or that's how I saw it
since paper and so I got really excited
about it and I just found like it was
unlocking all sorts of like fun sides of
my personality and and the way that I
that I want to see tools that we hadn't
really unlocked with some of the other
apps and you know something that I
learned early on with paper was like you
know That moment of creation is very
powerful, right? We we tend to like
downplay that and think especially in
this kind of AIdriven era where you can
just kind of fix it later, right? Like
oh, you can you can edit it later, you
can do something later, right? I
learned, you know, very early on that
like no, if you can if you can bring
some of that power to that moment of
creation. So like as you're using the
pencil, it's responding to you in a way.
you start to use it differently, right?
It's this conversation between you and
the tool. And people will draw something
very, if you ask them to draw a flower
or something, they will draw it very
differently if you give them a pencil
versus an ink brush, right?
>> Yeah.
>> And that's the tool. And it's not it's,
you know, it's not just an effect you
can apply. You just discover something
different, right? And so a lot of a lot
of camera was trying to put those tools
back into your hands at that moment of
creation so you can see it in real time.
You know, what are you doing? What does
this focus pull do to the composition?
Right? And so that it was as simple as
that, you know, it's like, well, stop
trying to think of all this stuff as
something later that you can do in post
and try and do it as you do it in the
camera cuz now you start framing the
photo a little bit differently, right?
or you start, you know, backing up or
focusing.
>> That's the biggest one for me is when
you have high contrast
in your preview, you like I can kind of
see it in person and I can kind of see
it through a glass viewfinder, but when
you see it in the in the preview and you
can see especially cuz the preview's a
little smaller, it forces your brain to
do that kind of, you know, the trick of
like unfocusing your eyes to see the
shape of a composition. It it kind of
does that a little for you. And yeah,
just like you're saying, you you
discover accident like happy little
accidents and reframe your shot based on
that as it's happening.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I mean, the best some of the
best feedback we get from the camera is
from people who are like, "Oh yeah, I
downloaded your camera app and then I
just went out and started like taking a
bunch of random photos of thing." You
know what I mean? Like remember when you
do that? When you buy like a physical
camera,
>> you get excited about it. you just start
like taking photos of plants and like
ants on the ground and like
>> so many of the photos in my album are
just these there's a sudden big chunk of
my backyard and it's cuz I got a new
lens that weekend, you know.
>> Yeah, exactly. Some of my favorite
photos from our app are accidents, you
know? It's like I accidentally hit the
shutter button as I was putting it away.
So, it's like this really cool blur or
something. And so I miss some of that,
you know, and I think I think we're
trying to bring some of that back to,
you know, that moment of of like
capturing, you know, can you bring some
of that magic and and creativity back to
that moment and not just think of it all
as like, oh, you'll do something
interesting later, you know?
>> Yeah. H that's so cool. Uh I could wax
poetically about this for for way too
long, but I've already taken a little
too much of your time. So, uh, I'll go
ahead and and kind of wrap us up here,
but not before I ask you the question,
ask everybody to end the show, which is,
uh, who's a person or people out there
who've inspired you and your work that
you'd recommend others check out? Well,
I would definitely recommend checking
out John Balisari because he is the sort
of patron saint of not boring software.
There's a great short film, this is
actually how I discovered him, a great
short film called a brief history of
John Baldesari
that is fascinating to watch narrated by
Tom Weights. I would also if you have I
know a lot of people have but if you
haven't dug more into Brian Eno I mean
he's just a fascinating person who
speaks very well I think on creativity.
A lot of people, you know, if we're
talking music producers, I think a lot
of people are are aware of Rick Rubin in
my opinion, like Brian Eno, I think, is
a better model for software designers
and and just has a little bit better
perspective, I think, on on creativity
and how to apply creativity. So, Brian
Eno, there's a great documentary on him
by Gary Huswit called Eno that you can
watch. It's like an interactive
documentary. So it plays differently
every time you watch it.
>> Oh, that's interesting.
>> And then he also has a book called What
Art Does, which is just like a tiny
little book where he talks about the
value of art, but honestly, I think it
applies to a lot of creative endeavors,
including design. So,
>> and then where can people, you know,
find you and uh your not boring work?
>> Go to notbore.in ing to find all of our
apps or search not boring on the app
store to find us. And then yeah, I'm on
the usual social channels, Twitter and
and the others if uh you're just
interested in hearing me rant about the
state of of creativity and and the app
world that
>> or seeing your latest uh you know uh
swag game.
>> That's right. Or or I also like to share
my private woodworking excursions. Yes.
uh and things like that. So, I try and
talk about apps some of the time, but
honestly, I talk about a lot of these
other
>> random things quite a bit.
>> Ah, perfect. All right. Well, thank you
so so much for coming on. This is you
like, like I said, like you came on the
scene in like 2020, which was right
after I started doing iOS development at
all. So, uh, it's very cool to to kind
of get to talk to you about this and go
very deep on all the backstory and then
spend a little time on the actual thing
we're theoretically here to talk about.
But, uh, man, this was this was a joy.
So, I really appreciate it.
>> No, it's great. Yeah, thanks so much for
having me.
>> So, thank you all for listening. Uh,
Launched is part of the Revenue Cap
family of podcasts. If you want to learn
more about the growth side of the mobile
app business, check out SubCub, which is
hosted by my good friend and colleague,
David Barnard. And of course, check out
revenuecat.com to learn about the
easiest way to grow and monetize your
mobile app business. And you can find
everything else launched at
launchedfm.com.
And uh I'll see you all in 2 weeks,
hopefully with my voice uh fully
recovered from WWDC. Bye.